A Guide to the George W. Litton Papers, 1927-1983
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
George W. Litton Papers, 1927-1983
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1981-099
3.2 cu. ft. 3 boxes
The collection contains the papers of George W. Litton, professor of Animal Husbandry at V.P.I. from 1940 to 1970. These papers date from 1927 to 1983 and include poetry, essays, V.P.I.'s agricultural extension station reports, notes, lecture material, publications, personal and professional correspondence, photographs from Litton's portrait hanging, and bound compilations like "Foolishness, Poems, and Philosophy" that function similarly to commonplace books.
Litton, George W.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by Virginia Tech Special Collections in 1981.
Biographical Note
George Washington Litton was born in Lee County, VA on February 22, 1910. He married Maria Boren and had two children. From 1927-1931 he studied at V.P.I. and graduated in 1931 with a B.S. in Animal Husbandry. After graduating from V.P.I, Litton worked as a County Agent in Tazwell County from 1933 to 1939. He returned to V.P.I for graduate work and earned his M.S. in 1940, whereupon Litton joined the Animal Husbandry faculty at V.P.I. In 1942, Litton was named V.P.I.'s 1st Extension Sheep Specialist and held that position until 1952, at which time he became the head of the Department of Animal Husbandry. From 1952-1970 Litton served as head of the Department of Animal Husbandry. He stepped down as department head on March 1, 1970, but held the position of Director of Centennial Programs for the V.P.I. Centennial Celebration in 1972. Litton also served as Co-chair of the of the Bicentennial Commission for Montgomery County in 1976.
Throughout his career, Litton received several awards and recognitions for his work at V.P.I. and in the field of Animal Husbandry. These awards included:
Progressive Farmer's "Man of the Year in Agriculture" (1961)
Wine Award Winner for Teaching at VPI (1961)
Cattleman of the Year by Virginia Beef Cattle Association (1966)
Kentucky Colonel (1970)
Distinguished Service Award, Southern Section, ASAS (1972)
Fellow, ASAS (1973)
Member, Board of Directors, Warm Hearth Inc. (1974)
Distinguished Alumnus of VPI by Alumni Association (1979)
Saddle and Sirloin Hall of Fame, Portrait Presented at North American Livestock International in Louisville, KY (1980)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains the papers of George W. Litton, professor of Animal Husbandry at V.P.I. from 1940 to 1970. These papers date from 1927 to 1983 and include poetry, essays, V.P.I.'s Agricultural Extension station reports, notes, lecture material, publications, personal and professional correspondence, photographs from Litton's portrait hanging, and bound compilations like "Foolishness, Poems, and Philosophy" that function similarly to commonplace books. Many of the writings relate to Litton's career in Animal Science and Animal Husbandry and include such topics as animal husbandry (sheep, cattle, pigs), animal nutrition, and the agricultural profession.
The papers in this collection were bound in volumes previous to their donation, presumably by Litton. The materials within each bound volume exhibit no clear chronological or thematic order. Additionally, items from one previously bound book often correspond with the papers in another, with numerous article or publication drafts appearing in multiple volumes within this collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the original order in which it was received.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; Science and Technology; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- The Centennial Director's Diary, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 1-1)
- United States Bicentennial Papers, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Convention Papers and Programs, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Portrait Hanging Papers I (Part I), 1971, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Portrait Hanging Papers I (Part 2), 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Portrait Hanging Papers II (Part 1), 1980 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Portrait Hanging Papers II (Part 2), 1980 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Litton Scholarship Papers, 1981 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Comprehensive Report and Research Write Ups, 1962-1968 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Livestock Research Report, 1961-1967 (Box-folder 1-10)
- Livestock Management Course Materials (Part 1), 1963 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Livestock Management Course Materials (Part 2), 1963 (Box-folder 1-12)
- Livestock Management Course Materials (Part 3), 1963 (Box-folder 1-13)
- Sheep Articles and Writings, 1954-1967 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Writings - Beef Cattle Mostly, 1953-1968 (Box-folder 1-15)
- Letters and Articles I (Part 1), 1973-1977 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Letters and Articles I (Part 2), 1938-1976 (Box-folder 2-1)
- Letters and Articles I (Part 3), 1975-1977 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Letters and Articles II, 1927-1975 (Box-folder 2-3)
- Letters and Miscellaneous Items I, 1952-1972 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Letters and Miscellaneous Items II, 1940-1972 (Box-folder 2-5)
- Letters, 1932-1969 (Box-folder 2-6)
- Speeches, 1959-1971 (Box-folder 2-7)
- Poems and Writings, 1953-1969 (Box-folder 2-8)
- Foolishness, Poems, Philosophy (Part 1) (Box-folder 2-9)
- Foolishness, Poems, Philosophy (Part 2) (Box-folder 2-10)
- Poems I (Box-folder 2-11)
- Poems I (Associated Notes and Poems) (Box-folder 2-12)
- Miscellaneous Bound Papers I, 1970-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 2-13)
- Miscellaneous Bound Papers II, 1959-1967 (Box-folder 3-1)
- Miscellaneous Bound Papers III, 1954-1967 (Box-folder 3-2)
- Miscellaneous Bound Papers III (Associated Notes) (Box-folder 3-3)
  Scope and Content
  These notes were found inserted between pages 61 and 62 of the Miscellaneous Bound Papers III. As such, these research notes may correspond with the article beginning on page 61, entitled "Article for THE LIVESTOCK BREEDER JOURNAL."
- Litton Genealogical Study, 1983 (Box-folder 3-4)
- Speech by H. C. Besuden, 1981 (Box-folder 3-5)